Stephen K. Yasinow Collection of Thomas Nast Cartoons 1863-1882 (Bulk 1873-1875) PR 288
New-York Historical Society
Stephen K. Yasinow Collection of Thomas Nast Cartoons
1863-1882 (bulk 1873-1875)
New-York Historical Society
PR 288
0.25 Linear feet
The Stephen K. Yasinow Collection of Thomas Nast Cartoons contains 71 political cartoons originally featured in Harper's Weekly magazine between 1863 and 1882.
Related Materials at the New-York Historical Society
The Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections holds the Harry T. Peters Collection of Pictorial Newspaper Illustrations, which includes some Nast cartoons. Bound originals of Harper's Weekly,Frank Leslie illustrated Weekly, and other illustrated newspapers are held in the library's general collections.
Provenance
This collection was donated to the New-York Historical Society in 2011 by Stephen K. Yasinow, in memory of his wife, Constance C. Yasinow, artist.
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically according to date.
Scope and Contents
The Stephen K. Yasinow Collection of Thomas Nast Cartoons contains 71 tear-sheets of political cartoons originally featured in Harper's Weekly magazine between 1863 and 1882. In this period, Nast contributed well over 1,000 cartoons to the magazine. The majority of the drawings contained in this collection are from the mid and late 1870's, the height of Nast's renown. The cartoons in this collection touch on a variety of subject matter, but are always suggestive of his personal political affiliations and beliefs.
Subjects to note include: Criticism of William M. Tweed (politician and head of Tammany Hall), Civil War politics and support of the Union Army, post-Civil War politics in America, the use of the donkey and elephant as symbols of the American political parties, and support for Presidents Abraham Lincoln and Ulysses S. Grant. The collection is organized chronologically according to date.
Biographical / Historical
Thomas Nast (1840-1902) was a renowned nineteenth century political cartoonist. His work was highly influential in American politics at the time and is still regarded as a valued record of American history. His widely circulated cartoons are credited with helping to elect President Grant and to re-elect President Lincoln. He popularized the famous donkey and elephant symbols of the Democratic and Republican American political parties, along with the images of Santa Claus, Tammany Tiger, and Uncle Sam.
Nast moved from Germany to New York in 1846 as a young boy. His professional career began at 15 years of age, when despite having little formal training in drawing, he became an illustrator for Frank Leslie's Illustrated Weekly. He later traveled to Italy to report on the Garibaldi campaign for the Illustrated London News. Nast began his career at Harper's Weekly during the summer of 1862, following the onset of the Civil War. While working at Harper's Weekly, he gained a reputation as an outspoken supporter of the Union and the abolition of slavery. Following the Civil War, his work focused largely on exposing corrupt politicians, particularly William M. Tweed, who was arrested in 1872. He left Harper's Weekly in 1886 and began serving as consul general in Guayaquil, Ecuador in 1902, where he died of yellow fever.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
United States -- Economic conditions -- 1865-1918.; Prohibition -- New York (State) -- New York.; United States -- Economic policy.; Political cartoons.; United States -- History.; Illustrations.; United States -- Politics and government -- 19th century.; Caricatures and cartoons.; Caricatures.; Political satire, American.; Political cartoons -- United States.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.; Magazines (periodicals); Nast, Thomas, 1840-1902; Harper & Brothers
- Series I: Single-page cartoons
  - Trapping Guerrillas in the West, 1863, November 21 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Thanks to Grant, 1864, February 6 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Peace on Earth and Good Will Towards Men, 1869, January 9 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - All Hail and Farewell to the Pacific Railroad, 1869, July 10 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - "The Promised Land," As Seen From the Dome of Saint Peter's, Rome, 1870, October 1 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Die Wacht In Rhein, 1870, November 26 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Eve at it Again, 1871, January 7 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Put Yourself in His Place, 1871, March 4 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Our President Puts His Foot Down and the British Lion Will Have to Wriggle Out, 1872, July 6 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Shylock, We Would Have Money and Votes", 1872, July 6 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Will the Senator from Massachusetts Do This, To Make His Words Good?, 1872, August 17 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Romish Politics- Anything to Beat Grant, 1872, Aug.17 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Next in Order Any Thing! Oh, Any Thing!, 1872, September 14 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Wolf in Sheep's Clothing, 1872, September 14 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - A Midsummer Night's Dream, 1873, October 4 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - Keeping the Money Where it Will Do Most Good, 1873, October 11 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - Tammany Hall Will Whip Creation this Fall, 1873, November 1 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Transportation Problem, 1873, November 22 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - Victory Sits on Our Helm!, 1873, December 6 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - Justice!, 1873, December 6 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Emancipator of Labor and the Honest Working People, 1874, February 7 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Good and Bad Spirits at War, 1874, March 7 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - Jewels Among Swine, 1874, June 13 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - A Dead Failure, 1874, June 13 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Dog-Days", 1874, July 11 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - Who Ought to Have the Cardinal's Hat in America?, 1874, August 22 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - A Tammany Rat, 1874, November 7 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - "The Mysterious Influence of the New York Herald", 1875, February 13 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - Peace Insecure- Afraid for Her Life, 1875, February 13 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - Peace Secure- Safe and Protected, 1875, February 13 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Trouble Has Commenced- A Tale of Anxiety, 1875, February 27 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - Washington, Lincoln, and Grant, 1875, February 27 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - Any Thing but a "Pacific- Mail.", 1875, March 6 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - "A Republican Form of Government, and No Domestic Violence", 1875, March 6 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - Under Parole of Honor- The Ex-Officers of the Ex-Confederate Army in Congress, 1875, March 13 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - A Legitimate Question about Home Rule, 1875, March 13 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - Hammering Woke Them At Last, 1875, March 27 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - A Moonshine Scene, 1875, March 27 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Good (pure white) Shepherd, 1875, April 3 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Eternal Vigilance is the Price of Liberty", 1875, April 10 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - The American River Ganges, 1875, May 8 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - The Next Pardon in the Reform Farce, 1875, May 15 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - No Church Need Apply, 1875, May 8 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - Another Feather in Yankee Doodle's Hat, 1875, May 15 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - Captured at Last, 1875, June 5 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - This Tub Has No Bottom to Stand on, 1875, June 5 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - HONI-SOIT-QUI-MAL-Y-PENSE, 1875, June 12 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - "News" in Washington, 1875, June 19 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - We Are Not Proud, 1875, June 19 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - The "Third Term" Trap, 1875, June 26 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - More Food for the Cannibal Press, 1875, August 7 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - Princip-Als Not Men, 1875, August 7 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - The British Lion Loose in the House of Commons, 1875, August 14 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - The Lion of the Season (No More Spread Eagle), 1875, August 21 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - Off the Scent, 1875, August 14 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - The Established (Foreign) Church in Ohio, 1875, August 28 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Words, Words, Words"- Shakespeare, 1875, September 4 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - That Irredeemable Rag Baby, 1875, September 4 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Holy Murder!!!", 1875, October 9 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - The Pope's Big Toe, 1875, October 30 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - Pitiful Reform, 1875, October 30 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - It Sounds Well! The Prologue Before the Farce, 1875, November 6 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - Out of One into Another?, 1875, November 6 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - Thanksgiving Finance, 1875, December 4 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - The Two Ring Tailors, 1875, Deecember 4 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - J.G.B. in His Property Room, 1875, December 25 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Is This a Republican Form of Government? Is This the Equal Protection of the Laws?", 1876, September 2 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - The Veto, 1882, April 15 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - The Lion's Generosity, 1882, June 24 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - One Bright Light on a Dark Subject, 1882, August 5 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - President Arthur, Hit Him Again! Don't Let the Vulture Become our National Bird!, 1882, August 12 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
- Series II: Double-page cartoons
  - Our Modern Canute at Long Branch, 1873 October 11 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Satan, Don't Get Thee Behind Me!" -- Any Thing To Get Possession, 1872 August 17 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - Let Us Think Twice Before We Let Loose The Dogs Of War, 1878 December 13 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Same Old Pirate Afloat Again, 1874 September 19 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Same Ultamontane Cat All Over the World, 1875 April 3 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - Beware!, 1875 July 3 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Visez the Rest of their Passports!" (Will Saint Peter Recognize Them?), 1875 August 21 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - A Challenge to All Nations, 1875 August 28 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Good-Bye!", 1875 December 25 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Fairest of the Fair, 1876 June 3 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - A Belle Savage, 1876 September 2 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)